<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-20T00:34:51+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>PhD Candidate at the University of Missouri. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Wellbeing and technopoly</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/wellbeing-and-technopoly/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wellbeing and technopoly"/><published>2025-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/wellbeing-and-technopoly</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/wellbeing-and-technopoly/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing-and-technopoly.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing-and-technopoly.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>This month’s book selection mixes the themes of wellbeing, love, and technology, with a focus on how they intersect in our lives.</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-februrary-2025">Books Read in Februrary 2025</h2> <ol> <li>Amusing Ourselves to Death</li> <li>Attached</li> <li>Technopoly</li> <li>All About Love</li> <li>Wellbeing</li> </ol> <h2 id="quite-amusing-all-things-considered">Quite amusing all things considered</h2> <p>Neil Postman’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Amusing-Ourselves-Death-Discourse-Business/dp/014303653X">Amusing Ourselves to Death</a> is a classic critique of television and its impact on public discourse. In it, he argues that the medium of television (translation: modern social media) has transformed serious discourse into entertainment, leading to a society more concerned with amusement than with critical thought.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/amusing-ourselves-to-death-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/amusing-ourselves-to-death-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/amusing-ourselves-to-death-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/amusing-ourselves-to-death.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="the-science-of-human-attachment">The science of human attachment</h2> <p>A canonical work, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Attached-Science-Adult-Attachment-YouFind/dp/1585429139">Attached</a> by Amir Levine and Rachel Heller explores the science of adult attachment styles and how they affect our relationships. The book provides insights into how understanding your own attachment style can lead to healthier, more fulfilling relationships.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/attached-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/attached-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/attached-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/attached.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="technocracy-to-technopoly">Technocracy to technopoly</h2> <p>Neil Postman’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Technopoly-Surrender-Technology-Neil-Postman/dp/0679745408">Technopoly</a> is a thought-provoking examination of how technology has come to dominate our culture. Postman argues that we have surrendered our autonomy to technology, allowing it to dictate the terms of our lives. He warns against the dangers of a society that prioritizes technological advancement over human values and ethics.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/technopoly-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/technopoly-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/technopoly-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/technopoly.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="love-with-fewer-limits">Love with fewer limits</h2> <p>Bell Hooks’ <a href="https://www.amazon.com/All-About-Love-New-Visions/dp/0060959479">All About Love</a> is a demanding yet profound exploration of love in its many forms. In this work, Hooks challenges the conventional notions of love, urging us to redefine it as a practice of mutual respect, care, and understanding directed toward one’s growth.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/all-about-love-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/all-about-love-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/all-about-love-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/all-about-love.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="the-pursuit-of-wellbeing">The pursuit of wellbeing</h2> <p>Lastly for this month, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Wellbeing-Essential-Elements-Tom-Rath/dp/1595620400">Wellbeing</a> by Tom Rath and Jim Harter provides a comprehensive look at the elements that contribute to one’s overall wellbeing. The authors argue that wellbeing is not just the absence of illness but a holistic state that encompasses (1) career, (2) social, (3) financial, (4) physical, and (5) community wellbeing (in order of the magnitude of effect on one’s overall wellbeing). Importantly, the authors provide practical strategies for enhancing wellbeing in our lives.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/03_2025/wellbeing.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Upward and onward.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in February 2025.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slow Carb and Sugar Rush Science</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/slow-carb-and-sugar-rush-science/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slow Carb and Sugar Rush Science"/><published>2025-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/slow-carb-and-sugar-rush-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/slow-carb-and-sugar-rush-science/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/slow-carb-and-sugar-rush-science.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/slow-carb-and-sugar-rush-science.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>This (naive) post is all about science and life as I currently see it.</p> <h2 id="sugar-rush-science">Sugar rush science</h2> <p>Those who have had the opportunity to conduct or engage in scientific research have likely experienced the blistering (sugar rush) pace of inquiry that quickly ensues. In this competitive landscape, timing is nearly everything, and being left behind can be detrimental for one’s continued career in science. Moreover, one is often seen as a scientific thought leader for being the first to publicize a novel insight or development, which is likely a positive thing. However, in this post, I would like to challenge readers (and certainly myself) to expand one’s viewpoint on this topic, as the future of science (and life) depends, in part, on how we normalize the pace of our work.</p> <h2 id="slow-carb-science">Slow carb science</h2> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seasonality">Seasonality</a> is a core component of <a href="https://calnewport.com/my-new-book-slow-productivity/">slow productivity</a>, a rebuttal to the annual trend of increasing the pace of our lives. After the COVID-19 pandemic, many knowledge workers (not only researchers) could identify the impact that full-time remote work had on their sense of personal and professional sustainability. Burnout (an opaquely defined concept, which may be related to a long-term misalignment with one’s values) gripped many individuals and drove them to seek new work arrangements or lifestyles. However, the scientific (work) “treadmill” continued (and continues) to zoom forward. If we are to identify a sustainable means of structuring our work, we must start with the fundamental questions, “What are my values?” and “Am I OK as is?”. If the answer to either is fuzzy, we are most likely treading through our lives with “unstable footing” (as I have often experienced for myself). Moreover, I argue that the nature of the work we choose to do (and ultimately may accomplish) is a function of these values and self-views (e.g., a short-term value system may lead to narrow and uninspired research).</p> <p>It takes tremendous courage and commitment to adopt a <a href="https://teachingcommons.stanford.edu/teaching-guides/foundations-course-design/learning-activities/growth-mindset-and-enhanced-learning">growth mindset</a> not just for our professional lives <em>but also for our relationships and personal development</em>. Part of this growth may include honestly assessing what we want out of life (by way of our value system) and what we are willing to give up for the loved ones in our lives (also part of our value system). In these internal dialogues, it is easy to mistake one of our many <a href="https://ifs-institute.com/">parts</a> for <em>ourselves</em>, which underscores how important it is for us to intentionally bake in an <a href="https://www.enneagraminstitute.com/how-the-enneagram-system-works/">integration</a> practice into our daily schedules. This has become an essential part of my daily routine, and I recommend those interested in learning more to explore frameworks such as Internal Family Systems or the Enneagram to discover more of what may be waiting to be discovered. As we discover more of our core values and patterns, we can begin to do the hard work of integrating our personalities through relationships and professional commitments built on intentionality and vision.</p> <h2 id="strategic-splurges">Strategic splurges</h2> <p>With deep insights about ourselves and those in our lives, we can start practicing seasonality in all its richness, <a href="https://calnewport.com/deep-work-rules-for-focused-success-in-a-distracted-world/">deeply working</a> with the time we’ve allotted to the task of building <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qwOdU02SE0w">career capital</a> and investing in our chosen communities. As in nature, there are times for scurry and times for limited hurry, and the ratio of the two should hopefully be small and predictable (to some degree). In fact, this intrinsic pacing may yield <em>better</em> and faster results in our professional pursuits due to increased clarity (i.e., not fooling ourselves and letting <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gradient_descent">gradient descent</a> lead the way). It’s hard to imagine such a trajectory played out in our lives will not impact what kinds of work we choose to spend our limited time on.</p> <p>Cheers.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Musings"/><category term="Science"/><category term="Philosophy"/><category term="Inquiry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A naive musing on the philosophy of scientific research and beyond.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The principles of tomorrow</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The principles of tomorrow"/><published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-principles-of-tomorrow.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>What do artificial intelligence, hedge funds, and personality frameworks have in common? They are all featured in this month’s reading list! Let’s dive in.</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-january-2025">Books Read in January 2025</h2> <ol> <li>The Coming Wave</li> <li>Principles</li> <li>The Sacred Enneagram</li> <li>Company of One</li> <li>Ikigai &amp; Kaizen</li> </ol> <h2 id="where-the-tech-world-is-heading">Where the (tech) world is heading</h2> <p><a href="https://the-coming-wave.com/">The Coming Wave</a>, authored by one of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mustafa_Suleyman">co-founders</a> of Google DeepMind, offers a balanced viewpoint on the current landscape of artificial intelligence and its likely near-term impacts on the global economy and workforce. Synthetic biology and its potential to transform medicine, energy research, and biotechnology broadly speaking is also a core discussion point in this book. Overall, if you are interested in delving into the technical and ethical concerns raised by computational super intelligence, this book is one to pick up.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-coming-wave-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-coming-wave-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-coming-wave-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-coming-wave.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="values-for-life-and-business">Values for life and business</h2> <p>Ray Dalio’s <a href="https://www.principles.com/">Principles</a>, now available in physical and audiobook formats, gives readers a chance to peek at the “operating system source code” of the hedge fund <a href="https://www.bridgewater.com/">Bridgewater</a>. In particular, this book details how its founders intentions of crafting a culture of radical transparency traded the common (comfortable) business practice of “saving face” by withholding one’s true opinions of business decisions for the incredible financial and professional growth the fund has achieved over the last several decades. In short, operating a business from a culture of mutually-assured accountability is far from an easy task, but Bridgewater stands as a case study of the power of this approach to leadership in the world of business and beyond. Plus, it’s easier to develop a familial-level of camaraderie when you can trust that others are being honest with you on any given day.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/principles-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/principles-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/principles-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/principles.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="know-thyself">Know thyself</h2> <p>If this is the first time you are learning about the Enneagram, if interested, I recommend exploring more of it with the <a href="https://chrisheuertz.com/books/">The Sacred Enneagram</a> to complement the popular <a href="https://www.myersbriggs.org/my-mbti-personality-type/myers-briggs-overview/">Myers-Briggs Type Indicator</a>. The Myers-Briggs framework offers a well-researched pathway to elucidating your personality traits, whereas the Enneagram promotes an intrinsic and somatic approach to self-discovery. Specifically, the Enneagram features nine key personality centers that individuals identify with to varying degrees, and each type typically integrates (or disintegrates) to another type in states of personality “balance” (imbalance). These integration pathways offer Enneagram practitioners a unique way to develop more “balance” in one’s relationships to others and self.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-sacred-enneagram-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-sacred-enneagram-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-sacred-enneagram-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/the-sacred-enneagram.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="staying-small">Staying small</h2> <p>Paul Jarvis asks the readers of his book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Company-One-Staying-Small-Business/dp/1328972356">Company of One</a> to reconsider one’s definition of success in business. In a world where bigger is often equated with better, Jarvis argues that staying small can be a more sustainable and fulfilling path for many entrepreneurs. He provides practical advice on how to build a business that prioritizes personal values and well-being over growth for growth’s sake.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/company-of-one-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/company-of-one-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/company-of-one-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/company-of-one.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="purpose-behind-the-hustle">Purpose behind the hustle</h2> <p>As described by Anthony Raymond, <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Ikigai-Kaizen-Professional-procrastinating-productive/dp/B0CN55C4JB">Ikigai and Kaizen</a> are two Japanese concepts that can help individuals find purpose and meaning in their lives. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ikigai">Ikigai</a> refers to the intersection of what you love, what you are good at, what the world needs, and what you can be paid for. It encourages individuals to pursue their interests while also considering their impact on the world. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaizen">Kaizen</a> translates to “continuous improvement” and emphasizes the importance of small, incremental changes in one’s life and work. Together, these concepts can help individuals cultivate a sense of purpose and fulfillment in their personal and professional lives.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/ikigai-and-kaizen-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/ikigai-and-kaizen-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/ikigai-and-kaizen-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/02_2025/ikigai-and-kaizen.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Leggo.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="AI"/><category term="Hedge Funds"/><category term="Personality"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in January 2025.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting off the new year</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/starting-off-the-new-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting off the new year"/><published>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/starting-off-the-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2025/starting-off-the-new-year/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/starting-off-the-new-year-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/starting-off-the-new-year-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/starting-off-the-new-year-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/starting-off-the-new-year.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Starting off 2025 with a mixture of classic sci-fi and non-fiction reads, here’s to the new year!</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-december-2024">Books Read in December 2024</h2> <ol> <li>The Comfort Crisis - OK, maybe I read this one earlier and just forgot to list it ;)</li> <li>The Fall of Hyperion</li> <li>Nexus</li> <li>The Song of the Cell</li> <li>Scarcity Brain</li> </ol> <h2 id="learning-to-be-uncomfortable-again">Learning to be uncomfortable again</h2> <p>If you have grown tired of the complacency that often comes from avoiding personal challenges or introspection, in <a href="https://eastermichael.com/book/">The Comfort Crisis</a>, Michael Easter offers some tangible advice and wisdom through his experiences hunting in the Alaskan wilderness for an entire month. Reflecting back on our ancestral origins, Easter highlights the importance of recognizing how the modern world can deprive us of life’s basic challenges necessary for human health and prosperity.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-comfort-crisis-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-comfort-crisis-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-comfort-crisis-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-comfort-crisis.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="time-calamity-strikes">(Time) calamity strikes</h2> <p>In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fall_of_Hyperion_(novel)">The Fall of Hyperion</a>, Dan Simmons demonstrates a mastery of world building and narrative structuring in only the second (and final) installment of a two-part sci-fi series. This entry in the Hyperion series capitalizes on the captivating world context Simmons established in the series’ first installment by carefully exploring a multi-character narrative through its natural conclusion(s). Gripping and stunning, The Fall of Hyperion represents a milestone in sci-fi writing that true (e.g., AI) fans should engage.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-fall-of-hyperion-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-fall-of-hyperion-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-fall-of-hyperion-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-fall-of-hyperion.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="carving-the-path-to-the-future">Carving the path to the future</h2> <p>When <a href="https://www.ynharari.com/book/nexus/">Nexus</a> came to my awareness, I knew I had to dive in, simply given Yuval Noah Harari’s exceptional ability to synthesize complex historical topics into an accessible narrative for us all to engage with. AI enthusiasts (and those simply concerned with the future of humanity and its societies) should consider reading this book to wrestle with key questions Harari raises in it such as, “If we can’t trust institutions (as flawed as they can be), what kind of societal structures are we left with?”.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/nexus-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/nexus-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/nexus-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/nexus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="lifes-song">Life’s song</h2> <p><a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Song-of-the-Cell/Siddhartha-Mukherjee/9781982117368">The Song of the Cell</a> reads much more like prose than scientific text, yet it contains nearly as much information as the latter (on the topic of cell biology and its role in our universe). In this book, Siddhartha Mukherjee outlines a compelling worldview of the singular becoming the basis for all the complexity we see in the world and how this rising complexity should inform how we think about human health and sustainability today (and in the near future).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-song-of-the-cell-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-song-of-the-cell-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-song-of-the-cell-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/the-song-of-the-cell.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="when-is-enough-truly-enough">When is enough truly enough?</h2> <p>Michaal Easter answers this key question with a Comfort Crisis follow-up titled <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/705376/scarcity-brain-by-michael-easter/">Scarcity Brain</a>. Using the social psychology framework of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scarcity_(social_psychology)">scarcity mindset</a>, Easter points out the subtle ways modernity has been engineered to manipulate our internal states of reward, pleasure, and risk tolerance to get us to become increasingly reliant on addictive technologies and products (to our detriment). For those looking for a way to break the cycle, reading this book is a good place to start.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/scarcity-brain-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/scarcity-brain-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/scarcity-brain-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/01_2025/scarcity-brain.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Away (to 2025) we go!</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Comfort"/><category term="Sci-Fi"/><category term="Future Socioeconomics"/><category term="Cell Biology"/><category term="Scarcity Mindset"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in December 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free to be creative</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/free-to-be-creative/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free to be creative"/><published>2024-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/free-to-be-creative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/free-to-be-creative/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-be-creative-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-be-creative-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-be-creative-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-be-creative.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>This month’s books center on the idea of learning, the creative process, and how to design one’s life around fulfillment. You know, simple topics. ¯_(ツ)_/¯</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-november-2024">Books Read in November 2024</h2> <ol> <li>Ultralearning</li> <li>Free to Focus</li> <li>Creativity</li> <li>The Almanack of Naval Ravikant</li> <li>Hyperion</li> </ol> <h2 id="learning-fast-and-slow">Learning, fast and slow</h2> <p>Do you ever find yourself wishing you could understand an interesting topic more deeply but feel intimidated by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome">imposter’s syndrome</a>? Don’t be! We are all novices in many facets of our world, no matter how generalized (or specialized) our skillsets may be. <a href="https://www.scotthyoung.com/blog/ultralearning/">Ultralearning</a> by Scott H. Young dives into the fascinating world of ultralearners, individuals who commit to mastering a new topic or speciality by dedicating a portion of their weekly schedule to acquiring the necessary skills to succeed in this new domain. Though the many case studies Young shares, by the end of the book, you may feel empowered to try ultralearning a new skillset you’ve always been curious about. Who knows, the process of ultralearning may teach you a thing or two more about yourself!</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/ultralearning-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/ultralearning-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/ultralearning-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/ultralearning.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="why-do-we-always-cram-jam-our-calendars">Why do we always cram-jam our calendars?</h2> <p>Looking at your Google Calendar on a weekend and realizing how much you have going on the next week can be simultaneously exhilarating and exhausting. It turns out, in a post-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attention_economy">attention economy</a> world, that constantly filling our calendars to the brim can not only burn out our adrenal glands (not really) but may also limit our levels of creativity throughout the week (more on this later). In <a href="https://freetofocusbook.com/">Free to Focus</a>, Michael Hyatt outlines this idea in depth while making the case for a more intentional structuring of one’s week, with the primary goal being to shift as many of your weekly activities into a zone of “Desire” rather than “Drudgery”. Doing so may not only improve your everyday experience at work but also increase your annual creative output.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-focus-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-focus-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-focus-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/free-to-focus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="the-idea-factory">The idea factory</h2> <p>If you want to take a deep dive on the psychology of some of the most creative individuals of our time, look no further than <a href="https://www.harpercollins.com/products/creativity-mihaly-csikszentmihalyi">Creativity</a> by the venerable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mihaly_Csikszentmihalyi">Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi</a>. This book will teach you that creativity looks different for everyone, but focused effort (and flow) seems to be a key ingredient within many of history’s most creative environments.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/creativity-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/creativity-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/creativity-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/creativity.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="how-naval-is-your-lifestyle-design">How naval is your lifestyle design?</h2> <p>Inevitably, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naval_Ravikant">Naval</a> would show up on one of my reading lists. <a href="https://www.navalmanack.com/">The Almanack of Naval Ravikant</a> takes readers on a whirlwind yet holistic philosophical (and practical) exploration of what makes life worth living (and how to live well in the modern era). For those interested in lifestyle design, this is a must read.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/navalmanack-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/navalmanack-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/navalmanack-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/navalmanack.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="finally-something-thats-not-self-help">Finally, something that’s not self-help</h2> <p>This monthly reading list would be remiss without including at least one classic sci-fi book, namely the Hugo award-winning <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperion_(Simmons_novel)">Hyperion</a>. In this first entry of the two-part series, Dan Simmons weaves an intricate web of character arcs and backstories into a singular narrative that compels readers to plow through its pages (or at least it did for me). I will say, I felt the ending of this entry was too abrupt for my taste, but at least the follow-up work picks up almost exactly where the first book concludes. If you like time-altering sci-fi narratives, you should consider adding this series to your reading queue.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/hyperion-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/hyperion-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/hyperion-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2024/hyperion.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Cheerio.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Creativity"/><category term="Pace"/><category term="Flow"/><category term="Scheduling"/><category term="Philosophy"/><category term="Time Sci-Fi"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in November 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Curious characteristics</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/curious-characteristics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curious characteristics"/><published>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/curious-characteristics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/curious-characteristics/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/curious-characteristics-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/curious-characteristics-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/curious-characteristics-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/curious-characteristics.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>I’m early in posting this month’s annotated reading. Here’s to good fall vibes! Let’s dive in.</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-october-2024">Books Read in October 2024</h2> <ol> <li>What Do You Care What Other People Think?</li> <li>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy</li> <li>So Good They Can’t Ignore You</li> <li>The Intelligence Trap</li> </ol> <h2 id="do-you-care-what-other-people-think">Do <em>you</em> care what other people think?</h2> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman">Richard P. Feynman</a> is arguably one of the most iconic scientists and educators of the last century, alongside towering intellectuals such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Einstein">Albert Einstein</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marie_Curie">Marie Curie</a>. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/What_Do_You_Care_What_Other_People_Think%3F"><em>“What Do You Care What Other People Think?”: Further Adventures of a Curious Character</em></a> chronicles Feynman’s life journey from being born a <em>modestly inquisitive</em> boy in mid-20th century New York, falling in love with both science and his early lover, to becoming one of the world’s highest regarded icons of modern physics. This tale spans the gambit from exploring the fragility of human communications and ego in large, bureaucratic enterprises to characterizing the value of scientific thinking in the modern era.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/what-do-you-care-what-other-people-think-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/what-do-you-care-what-other-people-think-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/what-do-you-care-what-other-people-think-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/what-do-you-care-what-other-people-think.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="the-framework-of-frameworks">The framework of frameworks</h2> <p>For the last 40 years, <a href="https://stevenchayes.com/books/"><em>Acceptance and Commitment Therapy</em></a> (ACT) has given rise to a new wave of psychotherapy. In this framework, <a href="https://stevenchayes.com/">Steven C. Hayes</a> outlines actionable steps one can take to regain connection to themselves and their core values. Disintegration from one’s core values - either by never unearthing them or by falling away from them - can often lead to dissatisfaction with the trajectory of one’s personal and professional life. To address this, ACT emphasizes helping individuals accept and reintegrate with their core values through specific actions one can take in any season of life.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/act-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/act-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/act-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/act.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="be-so-good-they-cant-ignore-you">Be so good they can’t ignore you</h2> <p>Inevitably, <a href="https://calnewport.com/">Cal Newport’s</a> well-known book <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Good-They-Cant-Ignore-You/dp/1455509124"><em>So Good They Can’t Ignore You</em></a> landed on my reading list this month (fortunately so). Cal’s writing has a way of drawing from many relevant experiences modern knowledge workers will be familiar with, such as questioning the <em>right</em> way to build a fulfilling career in a world of endless possibilities. Succinct yet insightful, Cal’s research presented in this work suggests that (1) chasing passion for its own sake often doesn’t work well for shaping one’s career and (2) as a consequence, most people are better off building <em>rare and valuable</em> skills (as defined by current or future market trends). By definition, such skills are <em>rare</em>, so without intentionality and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_(learning_method)#Deliberate_practice">deliberate practice</a> one is unlikely to (serendipitously) cultivate them.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="know-thy-biases">Know thy biases</h2> <p>In the spirit of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Kahneman">Daniel Kahneman</a>, <a href="https://davidrobson.me/">David Robson</a> warns readers of the dangers of relying on <em>intellectual thinking</em> indiscriminately. As Robson explains in <a href="https://davidrobson.me/books/the-intelligence-trap/"><em>The Intelligence Trap</em></a>, human minds are unconsciously prone to taking mental shortcuts and reverting to well-formed biases about how the world (or other people) work. Through countless startling examples of intellectual blindspots leading to social phenomena such as <em>meta-forgetfulness</em>, Robson cautions readers to reconsider the grounding of their well-formed views of how the world <em>really</em> works.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/the-intelligence-trap-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/the-intelligence-trap-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/the-intelligence-trap-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/11_2024/the-intelligence-trap.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Be kind(er) to yourself and others this month.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Science"/><category term="Values"/><category term="Passion"/><category term="Skills"/><category term="Biases"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in October 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What doesn’t kill an everything bagel only makes it stronger</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What doesn’t kill an everything bagel only makes it stronger"/><published>2024-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-antifragile-everything-bagel.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>For this month’s annotated readings, I’ve decided to combine the months of August and September into a single (everything bagel) post. You be the judge if that was a good call or not. ¯_(ツ)_/¯</p> <h2 id="books-read-in-august--september-2024">Books Read in August &amp; September 2024</h2> <ol> <li>Antifragile</li> <li>The Hero of Ages</li> <li>Trauma</li> <li>The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People</li> <li>Man’s Search for Meaning</li> <li>Making Sense</li> </ol> <h2 id="to-predict-or-not-predict-that-is-the-question">To predict or not predict, that is the question</h2> <p>Taleb’s more recent book entry <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antifragile_(book)"><em>Antifragile</em></a> discusses at length some of the lessons we can learn, among many other time periods, from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_Recession#:~:text=The%20Great%20Recession%20was%20a,to%20country%20(see%20map).">Great Recession of 2008</a> and how hubris and unfounded intellectual postulating led us to base many of the world’s socioeconomic components on shaky statistical grounds. <em>Antifragile</em> encourages its readers to rethink how (and whether) we try to measure risk and reward in modern (increasingly unpredictable) times.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/antifragile-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/antifragile-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/antifragile-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/antifragile.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="well-that-was-grim">Well that was grim</h2> <p>In <a href="https://www.brandonsanderson.com/the-mistborn-saga-the-original-trilogy/"><em>The Hero of Ages</em></a>, Sanderson concludes his epic Mistborn trilogy by exploring the classic “world end” fantasy trope in a refreshing light: What if the laws of nature themselves began to push towards obsolescence and indiscriminate destruction? How might that impact the psychology and motivations of the story’s protagonists? The series finishes its narrative on a steely note yet in a manner that spurs its readers to consider how else the story might have evolved. As Sanderson writes through one of his final surviving characters (seemingly in reference to himself as the author), “Finally he exhaled softly, his work finished.”</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-hero-of-ages-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-hero-of-ages-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-hero-of-ages-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-hero-of-ages.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="informed-healing">Informed healing</h2> <p>Paul Conti’s recent book <a href="https://drpaulconti.com/"><em>Trauma: The Invisible Epidemic</em></a> delves into the ubuiquity and effects of traumas (plural), both small and large, over the course of one’s life (in especially in the aftermath of the COVID-19 pandemic). In this book, Conti offers readers some empathetic and actionable insights into more mindful ways of reflecting on past and current traumas and how we as a society should no longer find it acceptable to stigmatize them or consider them “indelible character attributes”, to instead find ways of growing alongside them.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/trauma-the-invisible-epidemic-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/trauma-the-invisible-epidemic-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/trauma-the-invisible-epidemic-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/trauma-the-invisible-epidemic.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="high-vs-low-effectiveness">High vs. low effectiveness</h2> <p><a href="https://www.franklincovey.com/the-7-habits/"><em>The 7 Habits of Highly Effective People</em></a> has long been on my reading list and finally made its way to my earbuds (via an audio series). Stephen R. Covey certainly did a lot of research and “background study” living life before writing this book, because hard-won wisdom shines through many of its paragraphs. I personally think the live audio series version of this work is even easier to connect with than perhaps a traditional book version would be, since it features stories and examples from audience members’ lives that help illustrate the basic principles introduced in this work.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-7-habits-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-7-habits-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-7-habits-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/the-7-habits.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="a-meaningfull-life">A meaningful(l) life</h2> <p>As a world-renowned treatise on human suffering and resilence at its most extreme, Viktor Frankl’s book <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man%27s_Search_for_Meaning"><em>Man’s Search for Meaning</em></a> characterizes one’s experience of an existential meaning crisis precisely. What does man have left if even his family and health is reduced to its core remnants? Where can meaning and motivation to continue life come from in those <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_Night_of_the_Soul"><em>dark nights of the soul</em></a>? Frankl presents readers with a stark, realistic, and humbling portrayal of the human condition at its most basic, offering leasons in reflection for each new generation to come.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/mans-search-for-meaning-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/mans-search-for-meaning-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/mans-search-for-meaning-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/mans-search-for-meaning.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="making-more-sense">Making more sense</h2> <p>Lastly, for the month of September, I journeyed through Sam Harris’ popular <a href="https://www.samharris.org/podcasts"><em>Making Sense</em></a> audiobook, which is organized as a collection of hour-long podcast interviews grouped by complementarity or relevance for modern sociopolitical issues. Although some of the cultural commentary in this audiobook is now a bit dated, its discussions of ideas central to consciousness and intelligence I believe are still useful for navigating the world of today (especially in the public adoption era of large language models).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/making-sense-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/making-sense-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/making-sense-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/10_2024/making-sense.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Stay antifragile (and open to new ideas).</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Future-Proofing"/><category term="Growth"/><category term="Fantasy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in August & September 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is that a (well-dressed) black swan over there?</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/black-swans-anywhere/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is that a (well-dressed) black swan over there?"/><published>2024-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/black-swans-anywhere</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/black-swans-anywhere/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/black-swans-anywhere-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/black-swans-anywhere-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/black-swans-anywhere-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/black-swans-anywhere.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="books-read-in-july-2024">Books Read in July 2024</h2> <ol> <li>The Well of Ascension</li> <li>The Black Swan</li> <li>No Bad Parts</li> </ol> <h2 id="the-gates-come-tumbling-down">The gates come tumbling down</h2> <p>A strong kick-off for the month of July, Brandon Sanderson’s second entry in the Mistborn trilogy, <a href="https://www.brandonsanderson.com/the-mistborn-saga-the-original-trilogy/"><em>The Well of Ascension</em></a>, simply had to make my immediate reading list after finishing his classic Mistborn entry novel. This second novel spends a great deal of time uniquely exploring what happens after the heroes have won and have a new society to (re)build. The narrative structure no longer centers solely on Vin’s experience and instead expands to capture the psychologies and philosophies of the surrounding cast of characters, even in the midst of dire straits. Overall, this entry showcases Sanderson’s ability to repeatedly enthrall a readership with expansive world building and character analysis.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/well-of-ascension-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/well-of-ascension-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/well-of-ascension-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/well-of-ascension.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="how-long-will-this-streak-last">How long will this streak last?</h2> <p>Taleb’s venerable <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Black_Swan:_The_Impact_of_the_Highly_Improbable"><em>The Black Swan</em></a> has captured the attention of many astute and experienced practitioners of probability, planning, and investing. More importantly, it’s a charming yet chilling reminder of how blind we as a society are to rare (though technically probable) events. By default, we simply are not prepared for unexpected deviations from the “everyday norm”, largely as a function of our wiring for homeostatis (understandly so). However, Taleb urges his readers to make themselves personally and professionally robust against “black swan” events by (<em>full stop</em>) not trying to predict them in the first place!</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/the-black-swan-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/the-black-swan-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/the-black-swan-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/the-black-swan.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="the-internal-families-we-all-house">The internal families we all house</h2> <p><a href="https://ifs-institute.com/">Internal Family Systems</a> (IFS) is a blossoming topic in pop psychology today, yet its roots are over 40 years old, thanks to pioneers such as Richard Schwartz. To round out the month of July with a dose of “internal” work, I listened to the introductory IFS audiobook <a href="https://ifs-institute.com/nobadparts"><em>No Bad Parts</em></a> narrated partially by Schwartz himself. This book challenges many preconceived notions many of us have regarding “mono-mind theory” (i.e., the idea we are of one fixed personality at all times) while introducing readers to a new way of understanding oneself in light of a “family” of interacting personalities, each of different internal ages and (e.g., protective) wants and desires. Those interested in acquiring a new framework for understanding oneself and others may find this introduction to IFS helpful (and perhaps even transformative).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/no-bad-parts-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/no-bad-parts-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/no-bad-parts-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/08_2024/no-bad-parts.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>That’s all from me this month. Stay tuned.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Anomalies"/><category term="Fantasy"/><category term="Interoception"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in July 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where does the (super)randomness begin and end? And do alchemists have new competition?</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/super-random-alchemy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where does the (super)randomness begin and end? And do alchemists have new competition?"/><published>2024-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/super-random-alchemy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2024/super-random-alchemy/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/super-random-alchemy-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/super-random-alchemy-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/super-random-alchemy-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/super-random-alchemy.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="books-read-in-june-2024">Books Read in June 2024</h2> <ol> <li>Fooled by Randomness</li> <li>Supernormal</li> <li>Mistborn</li> </ol> <h2 id="is-it-stochasticity-or-is-it-just-me">Is it stochasticity, or is it just me?</h2> <p>Nassim Taleb’s well-known book, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fooled_by_Randomness"><em>Fooled by Randomness: The Hidden Role of Chance in Life and in the Markets</em></a>, instills in its readers a sense of humility and perspective on how randomness should inform our decision making, letting it guide our choices of investments to make (or not make), careers to development, and (perhaps even) role models to aspire to be like. This book left me with the question, “How do we separate the signal (skill) from the noise (luck) in the modern era of work”? The only answer I can think of is for us to become more precise with how we define and measure productivity and valuable outputs, an idea introduced in Cal Newport’s recent book <a href="https://calnewport.com/my-new-book-slow-productivity/"><em>​Slow Productivity: The Lost Art of Accomplishment without Burnout​</em></a> which is on my reading list for the near future.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/fooled_by_randomness-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/fooled_by_randomness-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/fooled_by_randomness-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/fooled_by_randomness.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="where-are-they-now-and-where-were-they-then">Where are they now (and where were they then)?</h2> <p>A slightly different topic I explored this month is that of childhood adversity and its impact on the trajectory and tenor of one’s personal and professional life. A go-to book on this topic, in my view, is <a href="https://megjay.com/supernormal/"><em>Supernormal</em></a> by Meg Jay. This work explores the character traits and seasonalities of the life of a supernormal individual who has faced above-average difficulties in life, and how such individuals can learn to recognize and adapt their core beliefs about the unique opportunities that their past suffering presents.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/supernormal-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/supernormal-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/supernormal-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/supernormal.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="should-alchemists-switch-careers">Should alchemists switch careers?</h2> <p>The final book I finished reading in June 2024 represents the first entry of the highly-regarded Mistborn Saga by Brandon Sanderson, simply titled <a href="https://www.brandonsanderson.com/the-mistborn-saga-the-original-trilogy/"><em>Mistborn</em></a>, and the first great fantasy novel I’ve read in far too long. What’s great is, the book is fairly self-contained, so if you stop after reading this first entry in the series, you’ve still gotten the main gist of this (innovative) world’s mechanics and structure. However, for interested readers, Sanderson offers expanded world building and dynamics in its two follow-up novels.</p> <p>The best way I can describe this book to others (when I’ve tried to explain it in ways any geek can understand) is this: Consider merging <a href="https://www.suzannecollinsbooks.com/the_hunger_games_69765.htm"><em>The Hunger Games</em></a> and <a href="https://www.viz.com/fullmetal-alchemist"><em>Fullmetal Alchemist</em></a>, and out comes something half-like Mistborn. The other missing half of the equation comes from Sanderson’s clever allomancy mechanics and thoughtful character development, which truly make this novel (as the scientists say) an <em>n=1</em> (pronounced <em>n</em>-of-one).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/mistborn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/mistborn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/mistborn-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/06_2024/mistborn.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>That’s all from me for now. Stay tuned.</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Annotated-Readings"/><category term="Probability"/><category term="Prediction"/><category term="Fantasy"/><category term="World-Building"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An annotated reading of the books I read in June 2024.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Org Mode Changed My Research Workflow</title><link href="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2020/org-changed-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Org Mode Changed My Research Workflow"/><published>2020-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2020/org-changed-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amorehead.github.io/blog/2020/org-changed-research/"><![CDATA[<div class="l-page"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/research_roaming-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/research_roaming-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/research_roaming-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/research_roaming.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="what-is-org-mode">What is Org Mode?</h2> <p><a href="https://orgmode.org/">Org Mode</a> is a popular extension of the text editor Emacs. It has often been praised as a means of codifying one’s daily activities and agendas. In an age when a litany of productivity apps and toolkits promise to increase your efficiency while at work, Org Mode remains a steadfast choice for the do-it-yourself (DIY)-oriented crowd.</p> <h2 id="why-is-task-management-important">Why is task management important?</h2> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Task_management">Task management</a> is necessary for making continuous progress on any project. Many different methodologies aim to encompass all the best principles of task management, and one of the most well-known and successful of these methodologies is called <a href="https://gettingthingsdone.com/">Getting Things Done</a> (GTD) introduced by David Allen. Its core philosophy is relatively simple: document each task you must accomplish in a given day to free up your mind to exert maximum focus on the task at hand. This process, as you can imagine, requires consistent discipline to execute it effectively.</p> <h2 id="what-is-the-connection-between-gtd-and-org-mode">What is the connection between GTD and Org Mode?</h2> <p>Org Mode allows its users to build <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Agenda-Views.html">custom agendas</a> as they see fit, further letting users connect documents, web content, and even emails together using generic links (e.g. Think hyperlinks for any kind of resource). Given this functionality, <a href="https://orgmode.org/worg/org-gtd-etc.html">others</a> have taken the liberty to create entire GTD-inspired workflows using Org Mode. Once again, the purpose of doing so is to ease the intellectual burden of having to remember each thing you have to accomplish each day.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/gtd_with_org_mode-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/gtd_with_org_mode-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/gtd_with_org_mode-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/gtd_with_org_mode.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="gtd-configuration">GTD Configuration</h2> <p>After several weeks of research (no pun intended), I discovered an <a href="https://blog.jethro.dev/posts/org_mode_workflow_preview/">Org Mode setup</a> designed by <a href="https://www.jethro.dev/">Jethro Kuan</a> that met many of my needs for a productive, organized GTD workflow. Like several others, I opted to house my GTD workflow directories inside my Dropbox directory to enable cloud-based syncing between all my devices (i.e. smartphone, desktop, laptop, etc.).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_org_dir-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_org_dir-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_org_dir-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_org_dir.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Out of the box, simply changing the GTD directory file paths to point to my newly-created Dropbox GTD directories worked great for getting my laptop and desktop quickly configured for syncing my daily agenda with Org Mode. However, I had to use a slightly different approach to sync my Org Mode agenda to my Android smartphone.</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_calendars_dir-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_calendars_dir-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_calendars_dir-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_gtd_calendars_dir.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>For this use case, I chose to download and install <a href="http://www.orgzly.com/">Orgzly</a>, an (at the time of my writing this) Android-only mobile app that can correctly parse and understand Org Mode syntax in .org files. What appears to be an IOS-equivalent to Orgzly, <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/beorg-to-do-list-agenda/id1238649962">beorg</a>, may also allow you to conveniently manage your cloud-synced Org Mode agendas. I cannot confirm this, nonetheless, as I do not currently own any iPhones with which to test the notion.</p> <p>In Orgzly, after configuring the app to point to my Dropbox-designated GTD directories (i.e. (1) dropbox:/Documents/Org/GTD/Org/ and (2) dropbox:/Documents/Org/GTD/Org/Calendars), I also chose to add a few custom <a href="http://www.orgzly.com/help#search">searches</a> that display tasks that are scheduled today (i.e. “Scheduled”) and tasks that are due today (i.e. “Due”). I tend to use the “Scheduled” search more than other searches as it quickly gives me an overview of what I have lined up for the day without distracting me with tasks to be completed in the future (GTD, remember?).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/orgzly_searches-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/orgzly_searches-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/orgzly_searches-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/orgzly_searches.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <h2 id="mindmeld-configuration">MindMeld Configuration</h2> <p>So by now, we have a robust means of scheduling each task for the day in a platform-agnostic manner. But how did all this affect my research workflow? To answer this, we’ll have to turn to <strong>MindMeld</strong>, a collection of thoughts, notes, and writings for my digital exobrain largely inspired by <a href="https://github.com/jethrokuan/braindump">Braindump</a> (also by Jethro Kuan).</p> <div class="l-body"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_mindmeld_dir-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_mindmeld_dir-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_mindmeld_dir-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog_post_images/12_2020/dropbox_mindmeld_dir.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>Much of the layout and ideas behind MindMeld has already been well-documented by Jethro in his <a href="https://blog.jethro.dev/posts/capturing_inbox/">blog posts</a> on pairing GTD and Org Mode. However, MindMeld builds on top of Braindump by adding several new <a href="https://orgmode.org/manual/Capture.html">org-capture</a> templates and directories. MindMeld also incorporates a running BibTeX bibliography that, with <a href="https://github.com/jkitchin/org-ref">org-ref</a>, can be used to cleanly arrange and index a copious number of BibTeX entries.</p> <p>I have used MindMeld to write several reports, proposals, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beamer_(LaTeX)">Beamer</a> presentations to-date, and I can say from my initial impressions of the system that it has drastically improved the speed at which I can put together well-formatted technical documents (references and all!). I have also been able to make connections between concepts that I wouldn’t have been able to make before thanks to wonderful Emacs add-ons like <a href="https://github.com/org-roam/org-roam">org-roam</a>. As it turns out, the diagram listed at the beginning of this article was generated using org-roam, and it hopefully gives you a taste of what is possible for making new connections between related ideas with Org Mode.</p> <p>I continually update a GitHub repository called <a href="https://github.com/amorehead/dots">dots</a> that houses my most up-to-date Emacs and Org Mode config files to make it easier for others to reproduce this GTD research setup. I have been primarily using the Emacs extension <a href="https://github.com/hlissner/doom-emacs">Doom Emacs</a> for most of my desktop/laptop use of Emacs, and I include in <a href="https://github.com/amorehead/dots">dots</a> a <a href="https://github.com/amorehead/dots/tree/main/doom_emacs/.doom.d">directory</a> dedicated to Doom Emacs-related configuration.</p> <p>My next focus will be on finding out whether MindMeld can be used to facilitate the entire research and development process, that is, whether one can effectively write entire manuscripts in Org Mode. I have suspicions that this may prove more difficult than initially expected, but I am still <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AP4LX8L7MFM&amp;feature=emb_logo">optimistic</a> about the possibility.</p> <p>That’s all from me for now. Take care, and keep in mind with great productivity comes great responsibility (or so I tell myself).</p> <p><strong>Alex</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Tech-Posts"/><category term="Task Management"/><category term="Organization"/><category term="Workflow"/><category term="Text Editor"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A high-level overview of my current personal setup with Emacs and Org Mode for research and task management.]]></summary></entry></feed>